So today's focus will be very much on
improving the models using search and um
there can be two kinds of search that we
will see one in code models where we are
sampling a lot and then we are searching
based on that and then u deep research
style search which you will see in
homework 3. So a lot of what we will
cover in alpha code and alpha code 2
those kind of search patterns um you
will use also in homework your homework
2 is focused on human eval. So this will
have this will give you uh an overview
of what to expect in simpler problems
and then even more complex problems and
then the agentic search this will be
closer to what you'll we will give you
in homework three. [snorts]
Um I think the broad thing that I want
to say with uh these models is that
we kind of know that the solutions lie
in the search space of the models but
how do you curate the answer out of the
search space of the what the model
outputs is roughly what we are covering
today.
So let's start with alpha code.
So the problem we want to solve here is
um a more complex version of the simple
coding agent problem. So if you use a
coding agent, what you often get is some
form of an autocomplete where you are
have a line and then the coding agent or
will complete the line for you. So this
is closer to a competitive programming
problem where you're given a programming
uh problem like competitive programming
problem. You're given a problem
description and then you're given some
input and outputs. So you have some sort
of a contract in that programming
problem which says that if you give this
set of inputs you should get these set
of outputs
[snorts] and what you want to really
solve for is how do we solve these
competitive programming problems so that
so the kind of things that we already
are able to do is code completions but
when we try to do blocks of code or like
solve real problems uh end to end that
that starts to be a much harder problem
as you'll see in the ways that this
problem gets solved.
So just to give you a preview of what ho
how um alpha code came about and like
what it achieved and it was this is an
older paper but it's worth remembering
that at that point in time when alpha
code was released which is almost like
four years ago
it ranked top 54% among the uh contest
participants uh in 10 contests and this
was the first time it was shown that AI
can generalize beyond just narrow tasks
and like solve problems end to
in and this was a much harder problem
than what you could do in just human
eval where you basically are given a
very small problem like complete this
function or you're given instructions to
exactly solve what you want to solve and
you don't have to reason about like
understanding the problem and then
figuring out what it would take to solve
the problem. So this was definitely
longer problem descriptions, longer
solution lengths and you were having to
understand from the dock string what is
the right solution approach even before
going and solving that. So it's not just
like taking the problem description from
the programmer and then just like coding
it up.
And I think this is well understood that
the when the models are generating
suggestions in one single line it's much
easier for us as um software developers
to interact with that and you get much
higher success rates for example in
copilot and equivalent uh functions. But
when you have to solve problems end to
end, that ends up being a much harder
problem. So if you look at and I'll go
through each of these block diagrams uh
one by one. Um so this is pre um
uh this is pre having large models. So
they actually were pre-training their
own models. The pre-trained models in
the next report uh will will get
replaced. So what you see here is that
you have a stage where you are basically
coming up with a model from which you
are going to sample. Now this model we
will later replace with
a large language model. So here they're
also doing pre-training and fine-tuning
and the data that fed that data that
really helped this model train was
GitHub data and then C code contest.
What code contest is basically a large
uh chunk of pro problems and solutions
that come from competitive programming.
So once they trained the model here,
they're basically going to do a large um
they're they're going to sample a lot of
solutions. So we have seen repeated
sampling before. So this is repeated
sampling but at a massive scale. So you
will end up with a lot of solutions and
then you're going to play some tricks to
figure out which set of solutions should
we even run tests on. So, so far we've
just been closing the loop where we take
whatever set of solutions the model
outputs and then running tests on them.
In this particular case, you're actually
going to select. So, there's a selection
stage before you're going to complete
and execute and evaluate.
So, just to walk through things step by
step and and uh so the first step is
pre-training.
You're going to pre-train a model. In
this particular case, they're going to
use mass language model loss. You can
also have a decoder only model which
we'll see shortly. And the model is
trained on GitHub code uh about 700 GB
of that trained with next token
prediction.
What's interesting is that when they
fine-tune it, they are using some
tricks. So they're using regularization
so that they can assign higher
probability to more meaningful patterns.
This is interesting in code. And then
they're doing something called as value
conditioning um and prediction. Uh so
the thing that I want to highlight in
this slide is that what they in the
regularization technique when they're
doing fine-tuning they assign higher
weight to higher likelihood tokens so
that there are certain tokens that will
have higher likelihood and then they are
putting lower weight to lower likelihood
tokens. So this is called as gold. So it
will help improve the precision. So in
the next token um next token uh
prediction loss they are basically
adding a waiting mechanism to take into
account uh the likelihood of the tokens
also uh which helps um in certain ways
and and helps to uh assign higher
probabilities to more meaningful
patterns. So this is done in the
fine-tuning phase.
So once you get this model that is u
able to and this was an encoder decoder
model that they were initially using and
then they also tried with decoder only
models in alpha code 2. Once they get
this model they are going to try large
scale sampling.
Uh they generate 1 million 1 million is
a large number they generate 1 million
diverse sample programs per question. So
if you have a question a competent
programming per question they're
generating 1 million solutions half in
Python half in C++. So machines can do
that and they randomize the problem tags
and the ratings in the prompt and they
use a high sampling temperature. So it's
like these solutions are going going to
be diverse
and once they generate these set of
solutions what they're doing is they are
doing some amount of filtering and
clustering. So they filter the samples
to only those that passed tests given in
the problem statement and then they are
clustering them so that they're
syntactically different but semantically
equivalent. So they differentiate
between that. So they are basically
uh using a clustering mechanism where
they use a separate test input
generation model train it to predict
test inputs given problem descriptions
and then create these new test inputs
for uh unseen problems. So they're
basically trying to figure out different
trick uh tricks to cluster this um this
test inputs the semantic equivalence
being one way to do that. Now the reason
this clustering is important is is it it
is effectively providing a way for us to
select which set of solutions are
diverse enough for us to then uh
evaluate to close the loop.
So now what you can do is you can submit
only a subset of solutions to the code
forces platform which is the actual
competition platform.
So and that will check the program
correctness. It will uh benchmark
against other performers uh best
performers on this task like human
competitors. But the challenge here is
that you cannot submit all the
solutions. So 1 million solutions cannot
be submitted to this uh platform. So
they have done
a curation phase, a filtering and
clustering phase to get to this stage.
Um and then there's also evaluation on
code contest. Remember that code contest
was used to train the model. So there's
a test set that they hold out uh which
will basically
give them a signal. So this is the data
set that is created by authors but they
can also um measure signal on this
particular data set to figure out if
their solution is supposed to do well or
not.
So when they first uh did evaluation on
code forc's platform um they ran like
they they took their model ran it live
generated samples filtered with example
tests clustered to get some submissions
and then submitted to the platform and
they ran this with uh they submitted in
10 competitions which each had 5,000
participants and uh what they found was
that their solutions with this alpha
code actually had an average ranking of
54.3 assuming 10 submissions per
problem. So not not 1 million and um it
was competitive with 28% of the
competitors in the last 6 months. So
this table is showing you that if you
looked at a certain contest ID uh how
was the alpha code model doing what was
its percentage ranking the best ranking
and the estimated ranking and the worst
ranking uh relative to uh other
programmers. This is more of a ranking
based as to like once you submit a
solution you're cap um you're ranked
based on the efficiency of your solution
and the correctness of your solution.
Before I move further uh questions
you go back to previous page.
It seems like the I mean I mean the the
the numbers table if you look at the
performance across different data sets
it seems that
>> this is different contest.
>> Yeah. It seems they did pretty well
[clears throat]
162.
>> Mhm. Even the worst one is like 50 some
the
>> but if you somehow it's like 16
>> like when is worse it's really worse
like 90% just I'm just curious why like
[clears throat] have a big variation of
how people come
>> um I'll ask you that question back what
do you think
I mean this is this is your pipeline
right
>> where where will the variance come from
so different contests will have
different problem inputs
>> maybe it's the two contests so the two
contest they perform well if the contest
are similar than the test
other
than new algorithm or new contest then
the algorithm may fail to or struggle to
answer because it doesn't include
>> okay
but I don't know if it's true
>> so the large scale I mean so what what
um what's your name again
>> is asking is that why do we get variance
across different contest ids and it does
well in one contest and does not do well
in another so at the end of the day you
are depending on
a uh how how close are these say contest
problems how in distribution they are.
So that's one pos pl pos pl pos pl pos
pl pos pl pos pl pos pl pos pl pos pl
pos pl pos pl pos pl pos pl pos pl pos
possible hypothesis the other plausible
hypothesis is that our [snorts] ability
to so in the large scale sampling that
would control like is one of the
solutions correct but then our ability
to select the right set of candidate
solutions might also be affected in
different contest ids right so the
selection stage can also be a bottleneck
here
like there can be solutions that are
almost correct but not completely
correct
Yes. Yes.
Seems like a very arbitrary. Do they
have an experiment that shows how the
model pass through uh scales as the
number of samples?
>> So I think they basically went so they
do have some experiments that they did
but I think uh it's sort of order of
magnitude. So with this particular model
size and there is some results I'll show
you. uh with this particular model size
they had to go for much larger number of
samples. I think if you remember from
earlier slides on test time compute when
you have smaller models you do have to
go for much larger number of samples to
get um the same passet Katur
>> so the saturation so let's look at the
results and then come back to that
comment but I think on the question
around why is it different in different
contests I mean the inputs are different
and then the pipeline will the selection
stage can be a bottleneck so both of
those influence
where uh it does well and where it
doesn't do well.
[clears throat] So there is two things
worth noticing. Uh so
when we when we compute uh solutions
with repetitive sampling in test time
compute and and this is something that
you're definitely using in homework too.
Uh you have this notion of passet K. So
that's the percentage of problems. So if
you get the model to generate case
samples and you submit all of them for
evaluation on the hidden test uh how
many problems will actually solve the
problem description that was given. It
measures how good is the search aspect
of the sampling process. So it's
basically coverage in the lectures that
we covered before.
uh what this particular um
benchmark measures is 10 at k uh 10
being the number of submissions that
you're going to go submit for
evaluation. So even if you get the model
to output k samples in this particular
case 1 million um you don't have the
ability to measure correctness on all
the samples uh for the final set of
solutions. So you do have to do some
selection um so or scoring to decide
which set of solutions I'm going to
submit. So it measures also the
filtering process of how well the model
will behave when you have a very large
number of samples. So you you're not
just generating samples but you have to
do some search yourself before you can
submit this solutions uh for evaluation
to hidden tests.
Now why does this matter? So this is
validation set and that's test set and
they train different model sizes. So
this is 9B model 90 uh 41B model. So
that's a larger model and then 41B with
clustering.
And uh what they're presenting is
validation set results for
10 at 1K. So this is the question you
were asking me. um they're basically
going to submit 10 solutions out of 1k
generated outputs and then keep
increasing that to 10k 100k and 1
million and then they're going to do a
similar set for test set as well. Um
and what you will notice is that
typically the larger model size
consistently will do better than the
smaller model size. I think that is
something we have talked about before.
Um but the other thing to notice is that
as you go for larger number of samples
which is something we have seen as well
you are able to do better. So like going
from 10 at 1K to 10 at 1 million you're
clearly doing better and same on the
test set side and um the clustering uh
so typically this we we had covered this
slide with pass at um number of samples
uh in this particular case even
clustering uh is consistently uh so 10
at 1K will definitely also improve
similar to pass at 1K and then if you
look at the last row here which is 41B
plus clustering. Well, you see that
that's consistently better. So like 9B
versus 41B versus 41B plus clustering,
the 41B plus clustering is definitely
going to still be better than um the one
before because it definitely provides an
improvement.
And and the reason for doing that is
because if you were to measure um the
set of solutions that the model has
output and you wanted to measure their
diversity, the clustering provides you a
way to like submit only the diverse set
of solutions if you can only submit 10
problems. Um and since competitive
coding problems are quite difficult, you
don't get much benefit out of uh
submitting the same set of solutions uh
to the evaluation process. So if you can
like choose which set of uh problems to
submit uh that helps
and u if we were to measure um just 10
at uh k and pass at k if you had u so
pass at k would be unlimited attempts
and 10 at k would be 10 attempts uh on
evaluating per problem. On the
x-axis you have the sampling budget and
on the y-axis you have uh this accuracy
in terms of um how many attempts you get
to solve the problem. The solve rate
definitely scales log linearly with more
samples. So this is very much in line
with what we had seen for pass k in
repetitive sampling. So even after the
selection stage we definitely see the
same log linear trend with more samples
and uh better models have better slopes.
So in this particular case you see that
41B which is the blue curve has better
sol uh sorry the purple curve of 41B has
better slope compared to the 300 million
parameter model uh at the bottom and
same applies even for passet K. And then
the final thing is that when only 10
samples are submitted um
then then you do get bottleneck in
certain ways. So you have to um you can
get higher accuracy. So if you compare
the y-axis 10 atk versus pass at k if
you have unlimited attempts per problem
uh which is a syn synthetic scenario you
are almost getting to something above uh
40% and here you are only getting to
30%. So there is definitely some
bottlenecking happening in selection
stage. So you are bottlenecked by how
you filter and cluster in some ways when
you have to choose which set of
solutions um uh will pass the tests.
Yes,
>> I just wondering like if this trend
continue you really get it to another
like another six or more like that will
be one trade. If you really get one
trading then the score if the tren
continue will be kind of double. So I'm
do you really believe like if we just
make it one trading we can just like
double the performance. Well, we going
to alpha code 2. Making the model better
is a slightly easier access than scaling
the number of samples that you're going
after. So on alpha code 2, uh the model
performance improves and that helps you
reduce the number of samples to get the
same performance or at 1 million you'll
get a much better performance. So this
is uh an older model but it's a weaker
model but the trends generally hold
>> and and and in some ways um there's a
I mean the larger models have done
better generally speaking but there's a
model capability gap so if the base
models are not strong enough they're
going to hit limits at certain point
>> if you really have no problem
so you really become of the in numbers.
You can just really do one one tree
sample with this graph like
>> if this if the log line trend continues
then yes that might be a project idea
worth exploring if the costs are not
prohibitive.
>> Yes,
>> I just want to say I think that could be
really useful if you think that one
problem is really important. you can
just pour your
>> on your computer solving that problem.
>> I think the challenge with that which is
something that is work um also that's a
good comment. So one of the challenges
with um solving it that ways is that you
kind of assume that if we sample more
the diversity continues to increase.
One of the challenges that we will see
in alpha code 2 and I'll emphasize again
is that you do have to ensure that as
you sample more and more you are getting
more diverse solutions and part of the
process of clustering is that it's
effectively figuring out which are the
diverse set of solutions. So if you
sample 10x more than what was sampled
here but you don't end up with more
diverse solutions then you're actually
not going to improve.
>> Is there a reason why we have a long
linear relationship here? Why why is it
not any other um modeling of wiverse
text?
>> So this was covered earlier I think the
um passet K versus unlimited attempts
this is uh theoretically derable and I
think the main thing that I'm
emphasizing is that even after the
selection phase that log linear trend
holds
um the passet K versus sample budget
this was covered in um I don't know the
lecture number but Aalia covered this
and that paper actually theoretically
derives it. This is the large language
monkeys paper or the one right after
that. Yeah, but if you look at the
derivation uh we can work through that
offline.
Um
okay so if we look at takeaways I think
the fun aspect here is that um we can
get high coverage
by sampling and then so this large scale
sampling this filtering and the
clustering approach you can get higher
coverage um and um they were able to
actually also make sure that the model
is not just copying existing solutions
it actually reasons. So they did some
search over the training data and
actually saw that u there was the
generated code was had some novelty. So
this was actually generalization out of
distribution. Um the challenge with
these particular set of approach that
they noticed that's worth highlighting
is that they were training the model on
loss and loss is often a poor proxy for
solve rates. So because um there are
many solutions that could have solved
the problem. So they did see that it
this model did not do well on uh say
dynamic programming or constructive
algorithms uh in some ways. So it was
not the strong in certain uh domains.
And then the other aspect was that it
was requiring a large scale set of
sampling. So that was not ideal in terms
of like how practical this was to be
used u everywhere.
Um if there was a time bound then um you
can imagine uh so if you if you
basically was just uh examining accuracy
then you want to make unlimited attempts
but if you want to do uh like time
limited bound in terms of efficiency
then you do want to like rank acceptable
solutions as they get generated. So that
becomes really important and um
as I already mentioned that more
difficult domains um required more
experiments. So this was not like they
the this solution approach actually
wasn't working well on difficult
problems and um in fact there it's both
a matter of like you might need more
steps to solve the problem. So this
particular approach in one shot did not
do a reasonably strong job. So
multi-step um solution approaches would
do better here.
So this was alpha code um summary. Now
let's see what can we do better. So this
was like 2022. If you look at the next
set of paper which is alpha code 2, they
improved upon this substantially and and
that was really helpful and we can also
learn um what were the differences uh
and that really helps us understand what
pushes the frontier even further. So
alpha code 2 started with a hypothesis
of what if you don't uh pre-train your
model you use an existing LLM. So in
this particular case this work was at
Google. So they decided to use Gemini
Pro um instead of like using
in uh training their own model and then
they want to customize it to get uh
better performance on this particular
problem set on co uh competitive
programming.
So the first set of changes that were
made were that instead of pre-training
you basically are just going to
fine-tune Gemini Pro. So it's not just
prompting they are fine-tuning the
model. And then um in terms of sampling
and evaluation for the large scale
sampling they want to ensure diversity.
So for diversity they actually had
multiple alpha code 2 models that allow
for massive sampling. So when they did
and uh go and do fine-tuning they
actually had multiple variants of this
model so that they get diversity in the
output sampling. And then the third
thing they did was that to select the
subset of candidates they had a scoring
model. So you can see that as a reward
model um which was used for obtaining
the best candidates. So it's not just
based on clustering and filtering which
is a heristic for saying okay this would
be semantically equ u semantically
equivalent but like there's diversity in
in syntax. They are actually now going
for a scoring function which can like
learn that function. So it's a learned
approximation of what should be given
high score and what should be given a
low score.
So um the new ideas here as I
highlighted was a that they are going to
fine-tune a Gemini Pro model to score
correctness before submitting. So that's
a reward model and they also had a
family of models based on different
hyperparameters. So different difficulty
levels, different tags. Um so they
fine-tune several models with varied
hyperparameters and then that maximizes
the diversity of the number of samples
they generate and they also improve
their data sets. So the data set that
they fine-tune on is a V2 version of
code contest which is actually open
source and then they had another high
quality data set for scoring purposes.
So going back to this diagram um what
changes next? So let's take a more
detailed look. So here if you look at um
the input model on the finetuning stage
you have this new data set called code
contest v2 um which is going to be used
to um generate now you're going to do
some tagging. So there's some amount of
just like take your code contest v2 data
set and put uh bisect it or rather
segment it into different data sets to
fine-tune different versions of uh
models that are going to generate
samples. So that's one set of like
intermediate alpha code 2 models that
they will uh generate. And then they had
another high quality data set they're
going to use to make this even better.
And this same set of model uh same set
of data will also be used to generate a
scoring model from from the same model.
And based on that they're going to uh so
this is basically a notion of like
there's a the data set is segmented and
used to tune multiple uh models uh based
to get more diverse samples.
Uh what's different about the data set
is that the problems and solutions are
higher quality and vetted and scored
better and the scoring model is able to
um estimate the correctness of the code
sample between zero and one based on
this higher quality data set. So they
manually curated um this data set uh got
uh more human annotators in place so
that they could uh train the model to
estimate correctness better.
And then the other aspect is that they
had this family of models. Uh instead of
having just one model. Now on the
sampling and evaluation side,
they split the sampling across models.
They in fact went to only C++. Earlier
it was C++ and Python half samples. So
they split the sampling across models
but only C++. And uh when they generate
the samples, they're randomizing the
temperature and the metadata so that
they can get diverse outputs. So this is
uh this is the massive sampling
pipeline. For each output, they're going
to execute on test input and they are
filtering out anything that's incorrect
and or doesn't compile. So they remove
95% of the samples. Uh at this point,
they're left with about 50k samples. And
then after that pro process they're
going to aggregate um and keep the top
10 largest clusters. There's reranking
on top of that uh based on the scoring
model to say like how likely is it to be
correct. So they score each code sample
uh and pick the best candidate per
cluster and once they have that that's
when they're going to submit and say
that did it win or did it not win. The
eval is going to be same as alpha code.
So if we are to compare results now uh
this is uh comparing alpha code 2 versus
alpha code. So alpha code so on the
x-axis you see the sampling budget. Uh
alpha code we were doing 1 million
samples. Uh here we're going to vary the
sampling budget per problem. And on the
y-axis you have solve rate.
Um as you can see that once you get to
100 samples you basically so alpha code
was using 1 million samples for alpha
code 2 once you get to uh 100 samples
you are achieving the same solve rate as
u alpha code and uh if you want to go
beyond that you can use more samples. So
the solve rate is still improving with
the increase in sampling budget. And if
you were to basically say how many what
is the maximum performance achieved um
alpha code 2 with u 1 million samples
was solving 43% it was getting 43% solve
rate while alpha code was only getting
25%. So um in this particular case even
though they're uh using the same number
of samples a better base model better
diverse solutions and then a better
scoring is giving them so this whole
system is giving them performance gains
which is almost um 2x relative to where
the previous system was
questions.
Yes.
95% of um sampling wasted on not
compiling or poor answer seems like a
very high cost. Were there any other uh
studies to see if there could be better
methods of sampling more reliable
answers maybe by like better prompting
or I mean like it did mention randomized
temperature but were there any other um
approaches?
So in this particular case, this paper
did not.
>> But if you are to refer to some of the
work that we have discussed before, what
would you need to do to
>> to improve that?
>> This is an older piece of work, right?
>> Yes.
I would I would um try the approaches we
took in homework.
uh like
>> like um better prompting or uh better
maybe using instead of like wasting all
of the compute on 1 million um sampling
maybe I would try to self iterate based
on one of the sampling at least once or
maybe at least try to have a better
method of aggregating some of the
information from the various sampling
>> right so I think what you're saying uh
so just to repeat the answer in homework
one you had done some form of
self-refinement so this is essenti
potentially parallel search in some ways
you've generated a lot of solutions and
then you are clustering on top of that
if you do a refinement process where you
have generated some solutions and then
you're saying okay if I can get any
feedback on top then can I improve these
solutions better that's one approach
that would like cut down the number of
samples but like increase the time that
you if you can collect any feedback um
the question I would ask is that how
would you collect feedback like what
would be feedback in this particular
case that's worth knowing
thinking through. I think the other
comment would be that if you can get the
model to do slightly better with RL. So
like if it can get better at solving uh
things um
with the RL loop in in between when we
cover train time scaling then that can
help cut down how much we need to put in
test time. So both those approaches can
like reduce the cost on the sampling
side.
Let's try that one.
>> So, so when it comes to practical
applications, so so when we are using
everyday kind of thinking models, we are
still talking about couple of dozens of
samples, right? I mean when it comes to
time scale and and then we hear about
this uh open AI 20k per month researcher
those are the multi,000 multihundreds of
ks of samples uh applied uh in
production. So I think the nature look
system is more of how you would build
the system that is generating those
dozen of samples right I think we have
discussed this before um for us to think
about these systems I think the big
question you're as asking is
how would you build the system to begin
with that can reason well that can close
the loop so I think there is a line of
research which has tried to answer that
question and what this is covering is
that if you started with an LLM and you
wanted to solve these complex problems,
how would you build a system that can
solve that problem? And then if you can
distill all of that knowledge into a
single model, then that becomes a large
reasoning model.
But this is a more of a
um multi- uh multi- aent system in
almost some ways where you're basically
having one model produce outputs and
then another model score it. And then
here a family of models is producing
outputs and then there is another family
of models that's scoring it. So that
gives you more tricks up your sleeve if
you had to like rearchitect the system
from scratch as opposed to depending on
what the current generation of models
can or cannot do. And the paradigm I
believe because at the end of the day
when we are saying in test time compute
there should be a solution in the space
of what model app was generated. Um the
paradigm is effectively that you should
be able to search that solution. So what
this is roughly answering is how would
you search for a solution
in the output space of what models
output?
>> Still a question. Yes.
So why the screen model? Yeah.
>> Say that again.
>> Why is the screen model?
Why is it like why the scoring model
only desire?
>> So I think the way to recall it is that
why is the scoring model not using code
contest v2? I mean you can train your so
the code conscious B2 there would be
contamination right the scoring model
should not see exactly the same data but
it does need to see some data in the
distribution right
it's it's basically a matter of you're
training the scoring model not
necessarily on the same problems but you
want to if if you're designing that
system from scratch how would you train
a reward model what you want to show it
is that for this kind of problems if you
had these two solutions which solution
should you prefer
That's what you're teaching the scoring
model or how what ranking should you
apply to that
you post train by the first design.
>> Mhm.
>> It's the same
data set.
>> Um
I mean you could have mixed those data
sets and then then done the same thing.
Yes. But that that is a doable exercise.
It's just multi-stage.
The it's not the same in the sense that
um uh when you do any kind of fine
tuning, if you're changing the quality,
then the model and if you're not mixing
the previous version, then the model is
forgetting some of the previous
information when it's tuning the in the
last stage.
Okay.
So if you were to look at the aggregate
results of alpha code 2 in terms of the
normalized score versus the um how it
would compare to human contestants
there. Uh and the way you would do that
is you would basically compare the
percentile of contestants who score um
at a certain level. Um what alpha code 2
was uh achieving is 85th percentile
between the expert and the candidate um
the master candidate solutions while the
human u and and it was outper like while
alpha code was outperforming 46% alpha
code 2 if you took two top two
performance on the like if you took two
top two solutions then it was actually
outperforming 99.5%
but overall it was basically scoring
closer to 85th percentile across human
contestants. So that was a big deal. It
was like okay in this particular code
contest problems in this competitive
programming it's doing very well in some
way. So that was a big accomplishment in
in one single year uh just uh with an
improved system
and I think uh for us what's worth
learning here is that we are increasing
the performance with less number of
samples. So we didn't have to like
necessarily scale the number of samples
but we had like better foundation model
and then the scoring model that is
selecting the best candidate is also
helping uh the solution. The
experimentation is still quite costly
and then as uh one of our uh classmates
pointed out this is very specific to
code and then a lot of the computers
wasted and generating samples that might
have bad syntax and so on that you have
to go and filter out. So one set of
questions that I have for the class at
this point in time is that
how would you uh change these methods
based on task complexity for example.
So actually I will pose that question
and then the other question I will pose
is um how can we embed reasoning
directly into these models?
take a minute to like talk to folks next
to you or
somewhere in the vicinity and then uh
let's come back and discuss those two
questions.
>> Let's tackle the second question. So um
how can we change these methods based on
task complexity? So if I easy problems
versus hard problems,
any takers for that?
Okay.
>> What you could do is uh you have like a
separate model that actually kind of
like judge each question based off it
being like easy, medium or hard. You
create like your data set where you're
sampling from also has those labels and
you just if you declare a question easy,
you sample more from the easy bank. So
it's like it's a better sample.
>> Okay. So is it more on the training side
you will change or is it more on the
sampling side that you will make this
change more?
>> Okay. So you're saying that um if you
have a simpler problem then you will uh
sample more from um
>> simple problems.
>> Okay. So you in alpha code 2 basically
you will use the model that's trained on
perhaps simpler problems. Is that the
suggestion? Okay.
>> Um other ideas
the sol did improve with model size
that's
or if you if you can identify simpler
problem maybe we can you can you can run
with less samples.
>> Yes. Exactly. Right. Oberve the model.
So this is something that was probably
seen in the repetitive sampling and the
test time compute as well as to like if
you have simpler problems then it's
likely that you can get coverage with
fewer number of samples. So you don't
have to go to 1 million samples every
single time. It's almost like saying the
model does is more likely to generate
the solution in the search space of what
it outputs.
So it should be easier to like sample
uh or or it's initial set of solutions
with some iteration with some iterative
refinement should be easier to correct
as opposed to like having to generate a
lot of different solutions. One of the
gains that you get if you generate a a
lot of parallel solutions is that you're
trying to get the model to provide
diversity in the approaches and you're
not trying to get it to like fix what it
already output.
What about the question four? How can we
embed reasoning directly into the model?
>> Okay, let's try out.
>> I think one way is that maybe you can do
more on the train set like in the train
set you can take all take all the
comment of you enough problems. So you
know in the step one like how it feels
like the framework of the solution like
in step one we know is a program the
problem so we
step okay slightly different than the
standard program so we need to change a
little bit so we have the final solution
the final solution
>> okay
>> so if we don't have enough common data
then we use llm to kind of pass the code
like to See the first section is about
what is the second section
for so it's the training they have is so
that part of the training but they have
is only the three like the second one
that
repeat
that's basically
>> okay uh so what he's roughly saying is
that you add hints in your training data
set around the solution of like what
kind of algorithm is being used to solve
the problem what's a more generic
version of that what have we covered in
that line of work.
As programmers, you think before you
write the answer. What if that thinking
could be captured?
If you added those chain of thought as
part of your training set or if you
remember the star approach where you're
getting the model to generate the
solution and then like give the hint as
the answer and then ask it to come up
with that reasoning then that that can
also be part of like how the model
embeds it. Right.
Any other ideas?
I think the other interesting thing that
was mentioned which is probably worth
highlighting is that if you have a more
complex problem then you might want to
decompose the problem into subp parts
and add hints for subp parts as opposed
to trying to solve the problem in one go
because these are hard problems.
>> Yes.
you tackle that for products that are
not like that sequential like maybe you
get like a you succeed on the first
intermediate output
>> has something flawed that is never going
to make the second part work.
>> So how does that sequential or like how
do you compose that work?
So I think the I think all of these are
hinting at like we do need to close the
loop at some point in a multi-step
fashion and almost want like a tree
search style of solution where you
basically want did I
I basically sample for say the first
step and is that roughly correct and you
want to sample for the second step and
then you want to be able to backtrack.
So it's roughly heading in that
direction but it's kind of um
early work that gives you hints. So it
it's basically gotten your thinking and
then perhaps that's your project right
but but your question is very relevant
as to like what happens if your answer
is correct in the first step but then
the next step is not correct
and um the task decomposition is often
relevant in that most problems have a
certain way of solving. So if there's
common abstracted patterns then that's
doable. But if you do expect patterns
that are out of distribution then maybe
uh you do need human in the loop
that's like AI scientist style of work
that folks covered last lecture.
Okay.
Okay. Let's come to the last part. Uh so
we spent a lot of time on just um code
uh and how to how to select uh set of
code samples that you can um that can
pass and and and um solve competitive
coding problems. Now let's look at how
would you do something like building a
deep research agent. Uh so search is
basically going to use large reasoning
models as the base and then try to build
uh deep research agents on top of that.
And um it's worth paying attention
because you will use this in homework 3.
So the key idea here is that you want to
use large reasoning models to retrieve
based on a query that you want to give
the model. So large reasoning models uh
have impressive reasoning but as you
know that most of these models are
trained on with some knowledge cut off
dates. So they typically will not have
the freshest knowledge. If something
happened yesterday, the model will need
to go look up that data. it's not going
to be there in the model.
The other challenge when you work with
reasoning models per se uh is that uh
they will go and output a lot of tokens
in long form reasoning but when they
have knowledge gaps they will be um
using terms that are um expressing
uncertainty. So one example is that if
you go use G u benchmark on GPQA data
set you will see uh the term perhaps in
the reasoning chains a lot or you will
see the term alternatively or wait or
so they're basically expressing that the
knowledge gaps will show up as
uncertaintity in the way the model is
thinking. So you want to bootstrap that
u in some way because otherwise those
knowledge gaps will continue to
propagate through the entire reasoning
chain.
Now one simple solution based on
learning from feedback or learning from
tool calls is that why don't we just
like take this query and get a relevant
document. Um so you take this query pass
it to a search tool and get the relevant
document. Um and then put that document
in the prompt and then out get the model
to output based on that. Why is that not
enough? So that would be more like
retrieval augmented generation. So
whatever is your question, you generate
a query and you get a document and you
put it in the prompt and then that's
what you use to uh retrieve the answer.
Now the challenge with uh that sort of
simple approach is that you retrieve
once at the beginning. So you don't have
the ability to like tweak things and
it's possible that if your search
problem is complex enough then each
reasoning step will need different piece
of information. So if you have a problem
which is asking just the weather then
maybe a single search call is enough.
But if you're asking to solve a complex
problem which has multiple parts uh to
solving it then after it gets through a
certain amount of reasoning it needs to
go look up additional information. So
for complex reasoning it's extremely
hard to get it right and same for
multi-step reasoning. So typically uh
retrieval augmented generation will uh
will improve uh will show improvement
over direct reasoning but in multi-step
reasoning it definitely suffers.
So the solution that search and proposes
is that the model generates the queries
um on the go. Uh so whenever it sees
these knowledge gaps it will trigger a
query. It will generate a search query
of uh what what tool calls to uh
generate and go search things over and
there will be multiple iterations in a
single reasoning session of like
fetching these documents. And the second
thing it will do differently and I will
show examples of that is that it will
analyze the retrieved documents. So
instead of just dumping what it
retrieved as the document, it will
analyze the retrieved document and
extract relevant chunks of information
from there.
and um it will only put these relevant
information into the prompt so that it
integrates well into the reasoning
chain.
So uh just to reiterate how this works.
So this is an original question which is
a chemistry question which is talking
about uh it wants to get the carbon
atoms count of product three which is
output of a bunch of different chemical
reactions. So if you were to use a large
reasoning model um you will ask the
model to start thinking it looks at this
term which I don't understand and
perhaps the model doesn't understand. So
it will go ask a look up what does it
mean? Now one trick is that it doesn't
go look up. So it makes a guess and
comes up with whatever is in its
knowledge base in the store weights and
provides a final answer based on what it
guessed. But if there is a guess here
and it got the answer wrong then those
things will cascade as errors into
whatever is the final answer. So all the
perhaps or all the uncertainty will
basically cascade into the final answer.
So your certainty for the final answer
is low.
Now one possibility is that you
basically whenever you encounter
unfamiliar knowledge you can now do web
searches. So that would be a simple uh
scenario of like okay unfamiliar term
basically go and do a tool call for
search return the document uh that
basically has that search tool for
perhaps there's a Wikipedia page or
there's a web page that has that
information and put that in the
reasoning chain and now like do the put
that in the prompt and then do the call
again and then provide the final answer
based on that. The only challenge with
this is that as you basically increase
your uh amount of content you're putting
there, there might be not as much
relevant content and these documents
like if you went and fetched like 10
documents that were related to the
information. Uh there's too much
information for the model to process. So
it might actually not still give the
correct answer. So in this particular
case, it was like 10 carbon atoms and
product three. Here's like 14 carbon
atoms. I still got it wrong.
What search oven is proposing is that
now you have uh whenever you get the
unfamiliar knowledge it will uh go and
search for helpful information. So
that's still a tool call to your search
but then um it will reason within the
documents. So it will try to look at
these documents and see if this is
helpful information or not. extract the
relevant content and then put it back in
the reason um in the next prompt like
what is the relevant chunk of
information to put and that will allow
the model to continue coherent reasoning
and provide the final answer here. So in
this particular case basically the the
ability to do this summarization of
information or reason within the
document uh really improves the quality
of like how it gets to the final answer
instead of like clustering the [snorts]
prompt with like 10 documents or 20
documents.
Um questions on uh what's the difference
between the three approaches?
>> Yes. Why does it say in the first one it
says oh perhaps gas why this little one
doesn't say anything because it's being
given the information right so the
uncertainity has reduced it is actually
being it's not even saying that in the
middle one which because it's being
given the right information in the
prompt
I think the harder part is how does it
know what to search for
it needs to know which keywords it does
not No,
like that that's the question I would
ask.
>> Yeah, it's a miser.
>> The answer is I think you basically need
to uh break down what are the key. So
there is different ways to tackle that
question, right? um if you're building a
real application, you want to identify
which parts um
you don't want to rely on the knowledge
base of the LM and you actually do want
to do a tool call because that
information is likely not what you want
to trust the weights of the LM for.
It's almost like you're finding the key
entities in your um question and
fetching information on those.
Okay. So there were two things that we
are covering here. So one is the agentic
rag and one is search. So I'll cover
both uh here. Uh let's first understand
agentic rack because then we build on
top of that in the the search forward
process. In agentic rack what you're
doing is you're basically every time you
are hitting um entities that uh you care
about you're basically going to insert
special tokens where you are going to
trigger a search and then when you get
that document you're going to insert
those results. So uh model is generating
some output tokens. when it's seeing
certain amount of uncertainty in its
output tokens, it's generating these
search queries between the special
tokens and based on that it goes and
does the tool call and the uh retrieval
tool will essentially return those
documents which will then be inserted
into the reasoning chain. So this is
happening in large reasoning models as
part of the whole reasoning process of
like it's also calling tools as part of
the reasoning process. Um so
that's one way to solve it. Um, but the
documents can be lengthy and they can
contain noise and oftentimes depending
on how good the long context
understanding and reasoning of the model
is, they might actually like if you put
10 or 20 documents, it might actually
not be able to do a good job at
reasoning over them. So uh the reason in
documents module of search 01 will allow
you to do analysis of each of the
documents of like how relevant the
content is and then it considers the
current query what it was reasoning
previously plus like this chunk of
information that it extracted and um
appends that to the prompt to allow the
model to continue reasoning based on
that. So it's essentially a multi-step
process within that retrieval tool
function itself because it's basically
getting that document information but
then also doing an extraction process on
top of that. It's it's almost like as
humans you don't want to just like go
and curate all the possible references.
You also want to take notes on those
references so that you have some way of
like um doing a better job understanding
and synthesizing that information. And
this allows the model to do um better
job at reasoning when we are adding
external knowledge and especially for
complex queries this becomes quite
important. Yes.
>> How does it previous reasoning and if
there's any corrections needed for the
previous reasoning how does it handle
corrections? So there is an assumption
that there is a state or there's a
memory buffer that's keeping that
uh it's not obvious in the way this is
structured but there's a basically some
form of like notion of like this is the
search query I'm trying to answer this
is and some buffer of like where is the
previous reasoning and so on.
>> Yeah.
Yes,
>> just add new in the engine direct module
on top of that you just like ask the
model to do some summation and then
continue reasoning. So does that like um
directly um transfer to the second style
like u
I mean like does this directly mix
method to be the be the new method
proposing
>> say that again you can just pick up
>> um I mean like if you just like modify
the prompt in the agent take module like
you ask the model to do some summation
and then and then continue the reasoning
does that produce the same um results of
wasting results.
>> So I think that's a great question and I
would encourage you folks to actually
try that out in homework three. I think
the assumption there is that if you were
to issue that prompt um you are assuming
that the the context length of the model
and the reasoning over that context
length is working really well. This is
basically agentic context engineering
style paper. So it's basically there's a
recent paper called agentic context
engineering. So essentially the
limitation here is coming from what can
you put in context length that the model
is going to do a really good job at.
In ideal world we will want that.
That's that's where we want to shoot and
hopefully by the end of the year that's
where we will be.
Okay. So let's to look at uh let's look
at the examples. So we were covering
this example of like carbon atom count
in product three based on a bunch of
different chemical reactions. In vanilla
reasoning the challenge was that it was
guessing the structure. So it definitely
got wrong answer in agentic rag because
you were um just retrieving the
documents they ended up being too
lengthy. So it did disrupt the
reasoning. uh in search process it did
uh search for this particular um formula
and then it refined it to a certain
structure and then that integrated
cleanly into reasoning. So essentially
the notion of like um extracting the
right information from the documents
really helps um search over and get to
the correct answer in this particular
case.
Now if you were to like go beyond the
example to results what we're plotting
is different domains physics chemistry
biology and overall um and you're
plotting pass at one on um
y-axis and then you're plotting the
number of documents that you get on
x-axis. So typically as you increase the
number of documents um for direct
reasoning and for rag the accuracy does
not go up but in this particular case as
you increase the number of documents you
are actually able to do better because
you can u summarize what is relevant
information or not in this particular
case assuming that the documents more
fetching more documents gives you more
relevant information related to the the
problem that you're solving.
So this is basically another axis of
like instead of doing iterative
refinement you can do parallel
refinement because you can basically go
fetch more information and then chunk it
down to put it in the model context.
Now if you were to um compare the
performance of um on GPQA data set um so
if you just compared GPQA data set in
physics chemistry and biology I was
showing you a plot in the last uh slide
human experts in physics chemistry and
biology on GPQA would score this much.
If you look at the reasoning models and
you build search oven on top of them,
what you notice is that um for example
in physics and chemistry um
search oven actually is quite
competitive sometimes even better than
what human experts would do. These are
hard problems by the way. So um and uh
in biology it's uh almost competitive to
uh say the biologist solving the
problem. uh one comment I want to make
is that you want to focus on physics
physicists solving physics problems. So
you want to focus on the diagonal here.
It's uh maybe not obvious like if you
change the domain then that's the number
you're comparing to. So the search oven
is doing pretty well in physics here and
in uh biology here and uh in chemistry
not so much
physicists.
So what's the level of this physicist?
>> Uh maybe they didn't do a good job
sourcing the physicists.
I think you're definitely getting to a
point where the models are able to do
well in certain domains more than the
[snorts] but uh this is not to say that
you're outperforming human experts. It's
more to say that you're competitive with
the human experts for this class of
problems. Yeah.
>> So there's still a lot of headroom in
chemistry.
[laughter]
>> Yes.
>> I have a question for the chemistry.
>> Yeah. you seen about even how this
chemistry like the you show the
chemistry formula can be more
>> I'm just wondering whether it it perform
worse in the chemistry just becomes the
chemistry part how to tokenize it can be
complicated you want to preserve the
meaning of sub combination but you but
if you just change one thing
>> the total chemistry like the behavior
may change dramatically so
>> I'm just wondering Whether just because
how do you better preserve like part of
the
like how to cocon?
It might be. I will let you actually go
try to evaluate on GPQA and see if the
chemistry segment if that hypothesis
applies. It is possible.
[clears throat]
I mean in every subject when you go and
prom these models the level of expertise
kind of varies for different reasons,
right? It's also possible the train data
set was not that strong.
So it's out of distribution.
And the other comment that I was uh
making earlier if you basically as you
increase the number of documents uh this
particular technique is able to leverage
the fact that as you increase the number
of documents you can uh improve the
performance just because you're not just
making the context longer. You're
actually um providing relevant context
from each of those documents.
Uh the other big thing that I want to
highlight is that in multihop question
answering this is particularly relevant
because in multihop question answering
you do tend to hit uh some amount of um
uh uh saturation in terms of performance
uh with standard rag. So and even with
agentic uh rag you do tend to hit some
amount of uh saturation. So in like
hotpot QA in two wiki music or bamboo
for example uh if you just did rag for
example you would not uh hit the
state-of-the-art numbers but with search
01 in um in a lot of these cases you are
hitting the the highest numbers the
bolded numbers um across that particular
line are coming from uh search1 as a
process so it is u providing a lot of
value even like in the multihop question
answering across multiple documents.
Yes,
>> what are the precision recall system?
>> That's a great question.
>> Like the retrieval itself is the
following, not the model,
>> right? So I think there's an assumption
here that you did at least for the way I
am explaining I mean it's possible that
you didn't retrieve the right documents
but if you look at the set of questions
I think the main claim that this paper
is making is that if you find multiple
relevant documents that are loosely
correlated to what you're quering about
even then like once you put all of those
documents in the context lump then
that's you're asking the model to do a
lot in terms of reasoning over that many
documents. So that's the claim that this
particular paper is making.
So in terms of like if you were to look
at the takeaways here um the gains are
definitely coming from the fact that
it's able to reduce the uncertainty and
um
the the document quality uh or like what
you basically refine knowledge both of
those improve and in the multi-turn
scenario um once you can figure out like
what you don't know um it's able to like
even after like refining across
documents it can do this iterative loop
of improving upon that so it can like
construct better searches over
multi-tonon scenarios. So in in this
particular case uh the reasoning quality
uh improves substantially because you're
providing more relevant documents and
then you're also figuring out where the
uncertainty is over multiple steps. So
effectively you have the right documents
and then you can correct yourself
because when you put the documents in
there if you're still seeing uncertainty
then you have additional searches to go
for. So there were some numbers that the
paper gives of like the number of
perhaps or or weight or likely basically
anything that quantifies uncertainty in
the reasoning chains goes down
substantially in this particular
approach. So they're basically analyzing
the reasoning chains of the model.
So um just to summarize what we covered
here is that
when we are building um deep research
sort of agents on top of uh say the
large reasoning models um that's a very
effective way to like uh bridge the
knowledge gaps that exist in large
language models. But just doing simple
uh retrieval augmented generation is
often not enough and even with um just
fetching the documents using tool calls
is not enough. you need to be able to do
that effectively over multiple turns and
then identify the relevant information
to refine which set of documents to
keep. So um the large reasoning models
by themselves often don't do a good job
in um scaling well if you put a lot of
documents in there. So this particular
approach allows you to improve on that
and uh larger models often do better.
And then um okay there's another paper
that I wanted to cover but like didn't
end up covering. So the search R1 stuff
um effectively varies from search 01 in
that it teaches the model how to go
search in an automatic way. So
uh what I wanted to say here was that
search R1 versus search O1. Search O1 is
closing the loop with a prompting based
approach. Search R1 can actually teach
the model to do this with an
reinforcement learning based loop.
We will not cover this paper um today
because we are basically at the end. But
it's worth going and taking a look at
that paper.
>> Um questions.
>> Yes,
>> I was just wondering considering the the
definition of a language model. So when
we generated an answer,
uh we supposed to have the ability to
put a probability of that answer, right?
>> Mhm. And I'm just wondering that when we
have this let's say 1,000
uh generations
>> each generation have a kind of different
probability or at least in some extent
and and has there been some correlation
between the right answers and the
probabilities or they are by by
definition they are absolutely
uncorrelated and and also same question
to to RA that when we have a have a rag
augmented
>> uh generation.
>> Mhm.
>> I I I can imagine that you know some of
the maybe it messes up some of the
definitions but is there any difference
in the in the uh in the in the
probability of the answer.
>> I mean that's a great experiment to go
do right. So let me answer the first
question and the second question you
will have to go experiment yourself. Uh
so in the first question typically so
there's a lot of studies but if you were
to just like take the output generation
and compute the log probabilities of the
output tokens and aggregate them in some
uh meaningful way like not just sum them
you'll have to do some averaging or some
geometric product or something. What
you'll find is that um the models tend
to be overconfident
about what they like overconfident. So
if you were to calibrate that to the
right answer, often you find that the um
the correctness is um like if it's 50%
correct, it will still be overconfident.
It will be like 80% very confident that
this is correct. And this kind of shows
up in the ways in which um if you try to
correct the model outputs, it will
sometimes be pretty [snorts] strong and
like no this is the right answer and
will not change its mind. Right? So in
some ways uh the model outputs do tend
have exhibited uh not high calibration
and like more are more on the
overconfident side. And there have been
research to try to get the model to
estimate the confidence say in a second
pass or or in a and try to like do RL or
like RLHF on top of that to get the
model to calibrate and and do things so
that it doesn't actually uh emit answers
that it has low confidence over. Right?
So there has definitely been efforts in
that direction. U different models
exhibit different behaviors. We don't
know which lab did what. Um so we just
get these notions of like oh the model
is hallucinated and
>> there is no correlation between the
actual right answer out from the 1,00
and the and
>> I think there is a correlation in that
uh if the answer is uh correct then the
model will likely get it correct but if
the answer is incorrect the model might
be overconfident in feeling that it
knows the answer that that's been the
the observed pattern but I think this is
what like this is worth studying this
there's The hallucinations in just the
ability of the model to know what they
know is an active area of research
and it's actually a a great set of uh
research projects if someone wants to
pursue it.